"When Zeus spoke, all the tribes of humans
"Quando Zeus falou, todas as tribos humanas
who live on the face of the Earth learned to sow and reap the fields."
que vivem à face da Terra aprenderam a semear e a colher os campos."
Karl, your pronunciation is off again.
Karl, pronunciaste mal outra vez.
I'm sorry. I'm trying my best.
Desculpe. Estou a dar o meu melhor.
But you've improved a lot.
Melhoraste muito.
When you first came here,
Quando vieste para cá,
I thought, "This is one heck of an awful student."
pensei: "Ele é um péssimo aluno."
Well, yes.
Bem, sim.
-How is he now? -Who?
- Como está ele agora? - Quem?
That Japanese physician.
Aquele médico japonês.
I heard he travels around the world.
Ouvi dizer que anda a viajar pelo mundo.
Is that right?
A sério?
I would like to meet that man again someday.
Gostava de voltar a encontrar-me com aquele homem.
Me too.
Também eu.
You got a job? That's great!
Arranjaste emprego? Que bom!
What kind of job is it?
Que tipo de emprego é?
I'm an interior coordinator.
Sou coordenador de interiores.
That makes sense.
Faz sentido.
I'm sure you must have one heck of an eye for good furniture.
Deves ter um bom olho para mobília de qualidade.
My work isn't quite the same as what you think it is.
O meu trabalho não é exatamente como pensa.
Really?
Não?
It must seem ridiculous
Deve parecer ridículo,
considering I've hardly spent even a minute in a kitchen before.
tendo em conta que mal passei um minuto na cozinha.
Maybe I'll have you do my kitchen.
Talvez eu a contrate para fazer a minha cozinha.
Sure.
Claro.
I bet any kitchen you design will cost a pretty penny.
Aposto que qualquer cozinha que crie vai custar muito dinheiro.
Yes, a bit.
Sim, um pouco.
You're not drinking, I see.
Vejo que não tem bebido.
That's right. Not a drop.
Isso mesmo. Nem uma gota.
Excellent.
Excelente.
Take things nice and gradual.
Continue a fazer tudo com calma.
There's no need to rush. Just like always, today will end and tomorrow will arrive.
Não é preciso ter pressa. Como sempre, o hoje vai acabar e o amanhã vai chegar.
"That's what happiness is." Isn't that right?
"A felicidade é isso mesmo." Não é verdade?
You're sick of hearing that, huh?
Está farta de ouvir isso, não é?
Happiness…
A felicidade…
He said that just knowing I was waiting at the station made him happy.
Ele disse que saber que eu o esperava na estação
Do you mean Martin?
Está a falar do Martin?
People are so mysterious.
As pessoas são tão misteriosas.
Our sadness fades away quickly, while only our happy memories remain.
A nossa tristeza desaparece rapidamente, mas as nossas memórias felizes ficam.
People are designed to have such convenient memories.
Somos feitos para termos memórias convenientes.
That's how we're able to keep on living.
É assim que conseguimos continuar a viver.
Let me introduce you.
Deixa-me apresentar-te.
This is Mr. Verdemann.
Este é o Sr. Verdemann.
He's the lawyer who cleared the charges against you, Mr. Grimmer.
Ele é o advogado que o ilibou das acusações contra si, Sr. Grimmer.
I found out as much about you as I possibly could.
Descobri tudo sobre si.
You were a product of Kinderheim 511.
Era um produto do Orfanato 511.
As an intelligence agent for East Germany,
Como agente secreto da Alemanha Oriental,
you played the role of a journalist and traveled the world.
fez o papel de jornalista e viajou pelo mundo.
You later investigated human rights issues as a freelance journalist.
Mais tarde, investigou questões de direitos humanos como independente.
You would carry an enormous bag
Levava um saco enorme
packed with mounds of documents to back up your findings.
com documentos que confirmavam as suas descobertas.
But one thing I was never able to discover was your true name.
Mas uma coisa que nunca consegui descobrir foi o seu nome verdadeiro.
"Wolfgang Grimmer."
"Wolfgang Grimmer."
It's not just his name.
Não é só o nome dele.
He left us without telling us anything.
Ele deixou-nos sem nos dizer nada.
Inspector Lunge.
Inspetor Lunge.
I'm not an inspector anymore, Detective Suk.
Já não sou inspetor, detetive Suk.
I heard you became a professor at the police university.
Soube que se tornou professor na Univ. da Polícia.
Recently, I've been able to talk to my daughter a lot.
Tenho falado muito com a minha filha ultimamente.
Though that's not accurate. We communicate by email.
Não é bem assim. Comunicamos por email.
Until now, my daughter and I lived our lives without ever speaking.
Até agora, eu e a minha filha não nos falávamos.
We knew nothing about each other.
Não sabíamos nada um do outro.
While we're alive,
Enquanto estamos vivos,
just how much are we able to truly communicate?
até que ponto somos capazes de comunicar realmente?
You must have had a lot you wanted to tell us…
Deve ter havido muito que nos queria contar,
over a nice beer.
enquanto bebíamos uma cerveja.
You're returning to Düsseldorf?
Vai regressar a Dusseldorf?
Yes. The company I'm working for is there.
Sim. A empresa para a qual trabalho é lá.
I see.
Estou a ver.
Will you be all right?
E vai ficar bem?
That place has a lot of memories--
Aquele sítio tem muitas memórias…
"Running from things is pointless.
"Fugir das coisas é inútil.
What's important is dealing with the truth and getting on with life."
O importante é lidar com a verdade e seguir em frente."
Isn't that right?
Não é?
Yes.
Sim.
You can get rid of this if you'd like.
Pode livrar-se disto, se quiser.
What's this?
O que é isto?
I'll be going.
Eu vou andando.
Okay. Take care.
Está bem. Cuide-se.
Let me know if you need anything.
E avise-me, se precisar de algo.
Dr. Gillen and I can help whenever you need it.
Eu e o Dr. Gillen podemos ajudar sempre que precisar.
Dieter and him too.
O Dieter e ele também.
Send them my best.
Mande-lhes um beijinho.
I will.
Mandarei.
"Questioning of Dr. Tenma continues."
"O interrogatório do Dr. Tenma continua.
"The full story of the incident is still unclear."
A história completa do incidente ainda não ficou clara."
"Testimony by Inspector Lunge begins."
"Inicia-se o testemunho do inspetor Lunge.
"Will this be Europe's most horrific mass murder?"
Será este o homicídio em massa mais terrível da Europa?"
"Dr. Tenma was completely exonerated.'
"O Dr. Tenma foi completamente ilibado.
"The police department indicates it will issue an apology to Dr. Tenma."
A Polícia vai emitir um pedido de desculpa ao Dr. Tenma."
"The motive for the murders is still unclear."
"O motivo dos homicídios ainda não ficou claro."
"Who is the young man who is the real murderer?"
"Quem é o jovem que parece ser o verdadeiro assassino?"
"The University of Münster Medical School invites Dr. Tenma to be professor."
"Faculdade de Medicina da Univ. de Munster convida Dr. Tenma para ser professor.
"Dr. Tenma still firmly declines."
O Dr. Tenma continua a recusar."
"Dr. Tenma joins Doctors Without Borders."
"O Dr. Tenma junta-se aos Médicos Sem Fronteiras."
The articles just get shorter and shorter.
Os artigos são cada vez mais curtos.
People are designed to have convenient memories, huh?
Somos feitos para termos memórias convenientes.
Hey, Dieter.
Ouve lá, Dieter.
You've sure grown up since I last saw you.
Cresceste desde a última vez que te vi.
Mr. Heckel, you've surely become a lot sleazier since I last saw you.
Sr. Heckel, tornou-se ainda mais seboso desde a última vez que o vi.
But you've still got quite a mouth on you.
Mas ainda és um fala-barato.
I'm sorry, I have soccer practice. I can't chat.
Desculpe, tenho treino de futebol. Não posso falar.
What? Hey! Hold on!
O quê? Então! Espera!
Has Tenma come back?
O Tenma voltou?
Jeez! He goes and joins Doctors Without Borders
Caramba! Ele juntou-se aos Médicos Sem Fronteiras
so he looks cool doing stuff that doesn't make money.
para parecer fixe com o trabalho voluntário.
I can't get ahold of him.
- Não consigo falar com ele. - O que vai fazer se ele voltar?
He gave me some work a while back.
Ele deu-me trabalho há uns tempos.
But considering the cost and labor, he didn't pay me nearly enough!
Mas, tendo em conta o custo e o esforço, não me pagou o suficiente!
Tenma gave you work?
O Tenma deu-lhe trabalho?
He said it was a simple search for someone, but it was a huge inconvenience!
Disse que era uma simples busca, mas deu imenso trabalho!
I even had to steal police secrets. What if I'd been caught?
Até tive de roubar segredos da Polícia. E se eu tivesse sido apanhado?
Hey!
Ouve!
Give Tenma this bill!
Dá esta conta ao Tenma!
If he can't pay,
Se ele não pagar,
tell him I'll make him do underground doctor work again!
diz que o obrigo a trabalhar como médico clandestino outra vez!
SOUTHERN FRANCE
SUL DA FRANÇA
I've been expecting you.
Tenho estado à tua espera.
You haven't visited in such a long time.
Não me visitas há muito tempo.
Well, I went abroad.
Bem, estive no estrangeiro.
Please share these with everyone.
Por favor, partilhe isto com todos.
My goodness. Thank you.
Céus. Obrigada.
Such lovely weather.
Está mesmo bom tempo.
All the leaves are photosynthesized.
As folhas estão verdinhas, em fotossíntese.
Life… Infinite numbers of genes.
A vida… Um número infinito de genes.
Do you know about Mendel?
Ouviste falar do Mendel?
Yes. He developed the genetic inheritance theory.
Sim. Ele desenvolveu a teoria da herança genética.
I attended the same university that Mendel did.
Estudei na mesma universidade que ele.
The University of Brno.
A Universidade de Brno.
It's a city in Moravia in the southeastern Czech Republic.
É uma cidade na Morávia, no Sudeste da República Checa.
It's a lovely place.
É um sítio adorável.
I'd love to visit it sometime.
Adoraria visitá-lo um dia destes.
Thank you…
Obrigada…
for coming here so many times.
por teres vindo tantas vezes.
I enjoy the time I spend with you.
Gosto do tempo que passo contigo.
Not a problem.
Não custa nada.
I'm in a very good mood today.
Hoje, estou de muito bom humor.
I have a feeling that I can tell you everything.
Sinto que posso contar-te tudo.
No matter how frightening it is.
Por mais assustador que seja.
You have…
Tens…
questions for me, don't you?
Perguntas para mim, não tens?
You are…
É…
the mother of twins, aren't you?
… a mãe dos gémeos, não é?
Yes.
Sim.
I loved him.
Eu amava-o.
He was killed by that man.
Ele foi morto por aquele homem.
It was part of his experiment.
Fazia parte da experiência dele.
I will never…
Nunca…
forgive that man.
perdoarei aquele homem.
Even if I die,
Mesmo que eu morra,
the children growing inside me,
as crianças que crescem dentro de mim
I swear they will take vengeance on him.
vão vingar-se dele.
My hand…
A minha mão…
Don't… let go of my hand…
Não… largues a minha mão…
Don't…
Não…
Who is… the real monster?
Quem é… o verdadeiro monstro?
Those children are alive, aren't they?
As crianças estão vivas, não estão?
Yes. They're fine.
Sim. E estão bem.
I remember.
Eu lembro-me.
Remembered what?
Lembra-se de quê?
I may not ever remember again,
Posso nunca mais me lembrar,
so I'd better say it now.
por isso é melhor dizê-lo agora.
I gave those children names.
Dei nomes a essas crianças.
Their names are…
Os nomes deles são…
Come in.
Entre.
Still maintaining your reputation for tardiness, I see.
Vejo que continua a atrasar-se.
You're ten minutes late for your appointment.
Está dez minutos atrasada para a reunião.
I'm sorry, Professor Kronecker.
Lamento, professor Kronecker.
Fine. I'll let it slide.
Está bem. Vou deixar passar.
I think you know why I asked you to come here today.
Acho que sabe porque lhe pedi para vir cá hoje.
It's about your graduation thesis.
Tem que ver com a sua tese de graduação.
Step forward.
Avance.
Yes, sir…
Sim, senhor…
I know that you've been through a lot.
Sei que passou por muito.
It must have been quite difficult for you to make up for your time off from school.
Deve ter sido difícil compensar o tempo sem estudar.
But that's no excuse for bad grades.
Mas isso não é desculpa para ter más notas.
Precisely.
Precisamente.
However, your thesis was…
No entanto, a sua tese foi…
best in class.
… a melhor da turma.
Of all the students I have taught, this is the finest thesis I've seen.
É a melhor tese que vi de entre todos os alunos que ensinei.
Very excellent work.
Fez um trabalho excelente.
I'm very proud of you.
Estou muito orgulhoso de si.
Thank you…
Obrigada…
What do you want to be?
O que gostava de ser?
A lawyer.
Advogada.
I pray that you can help many people.
Espero que consiga ajudar muita gente.
You may go now.
Pode ir.
Yes, sir!
Sim, professor!
However…
No entanto,
tardiness in court may earn you contempt,
não se pode atrasar para o tribunal,
Ms. Nina Fortner.
Menina Nina Fortner.
Yes, sir.
Sim, senhor.
Hello?
Estou?
Hey, Dieter.
Olá, Dieter.
How was your thesis? If you failed, you've still got me.
Como correu com a tese? Se chumbares, ainda me tens a mim.
My, how reassuring.
Que reconfortante.
Maybe I'll have you comfort me the next time I see you.
Podes reconfortar-me quando nos virmos.
Don't try to fool me! I can tell by your voice!
Não me enganas! Ouço-o na tua voz!
You passed, didn't you? Congratulations!
Passaste, não foi? Parabéns!
Thank you.
Obrigada.
But there's plenty of hard work to come.
Mas ainda há muito trabalho a fazer.
Let's celebrate! Hurry home!
Vamos celebrar! Anda para casa depressa!
I can't get back that quickly.
Não consigo voltar tão depressa.
I've got work and a lot of plans with friends.
Tenho trabalho e muitos planos com os amigos.
Are you kidding? Tenma's coming back, you know!
Estás a brincar? O Tenma está a caminho, sabias?
He just called!
Ele ligou!
But he said he has to go abroad again soon for Doctors Without Borders.
Mas disse que tem de voltar logo para os Médicos Sem Fronteiras.
When?
Quando?
He said he'll be back tomorrow. You'd better get here fast, Nina!
Ele diz que volta amanhã. É bom que venhas depressa, Nina!
Nina, about tomorrow…
Nina, sobre amanhã…
I'm sorry, I can't meet up tomorrow!
Não posso encontrar-te amanhã!
Tenma!
O Tenma!
I'll get to see Tenma!
Vou ver o Tenma!
Hello.
Olá.
Good afternoon.
Boa tarde.
BAVARIA STATE POLICE HOSPITAL
HOSPITAL DA POLÍCIA DA BAVARIA
You've been in a coma this whole time.
Estiveste em coma este tempo todo.
Can you hear me?
Consegues ouvir-me?
I spoke with your mother.
Falei com a tua mãe.
She loved you.
Ela amava-te.
I found out your real name.
Descobri o teu nome verdadeiro.
You had a name.
Tinhas nome.
Dr. Tenma,
Dr. Tenma,
there's something that I only want you to know.
há uma coisa que quero que saiba.
Back then, the monster came to me.
Naquela altura, o monstro veio ter comigo.
Don't!
Não!
Keep your hands off my children!
Larguem os meus filhos!
No! Stay away from them!
Não! Afastem-se deles!
This is an experiment.
Isto é uma experiência.
We'll leave one with you and take one with us.
Deixamos um consigo e levamos o outro connosco.
This is an experiment.
Isto é uma experiência.
So which one shall we take away?
Então, qual dos dois quer que levemos?
Don't let go!
Não me largues!
Mother, don't let go of…
Mãe, não largues…
my hand!
… a minha mão!
This one.
Esta.
No.
Não.
This one!
Esta!
No!
Não!
Did my mother try to save me?
A minha mãe tentou salvar-me?
Or did she mix me up with my sister?
Ou confundiu-me com a minha irmã?
Which one is it?
Como foi?
Which one of us didn't she want?
Qual de nós não queria ela?
I'll be going now.
Vou andando.
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
Legendas: Daniela Mira